This is the Air Jordan 3 Black Cement.
هذا 3 Air Jordan الاسمنت الأسود.
This might be the most important sneaker in history.
قد يكون هذا الحذاء الرياضي الأكثر أهميةً في التاريخ.
First released in 1988,
ظهر في المرة الأولى عام 1988،
this is the shoe that started Nike marketing as we know it.
هذا هو الحذاء الذي بدأ تسويق Nike كما نعرفها.
This is the shoe that propelled the entire Air Jordan lineage,
هذا هو الحذاء الذي أعطى دفع نسب Air Jordan بأكملها،
and perhaps saved Nike.
و على الأرجح أنقذ Nike.
The Air Jordan 3 Black Cement did for sneakers
فعل Air Jordan الاسمنت الأسود للأحذية الرياضية
what the iPhone did for phones.
ما فعله الأيفون بالنسبة للهواتف.
It's been re-released four times.
تمت إعادة اصداره أربع مرات.
Every celebrity's been seen wearing it.
شوهد جميع المشاهير و هم يرتدونه.
There's a site about what to wear with the Black Cement.
هناك موقعٌ عن ماذا يُلبس مع الاسود الاسمنتي.
It's been right under your nose for decades
كان تحت أنوفكم لعقود
and you never looked down.
و أنتم لم تنظروا إلى الأسفل أبدًا.
And right about now,
و حتى الآن،
most of you are probably thinking, "Sneakers?"
على الأرجح يفكر أغلبكم "أحذية رياضية؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yes.
نعم.
Yes, sneakers.
نعم, أحذية رياضية.
Some extraordinary things about sneakers
بعض أشياءٍ غير عادية حول الأحذية الرياضية
and data
و البيانات
and Nike
و Nike
and how they're all related, possibly, to the future of all online commerce.
و كيف يكونون مرتبطين، من المحتمل، لمستقبل كل التجارة عبر الإنترنت.
In 2011,
عام 2011،
the last time the Jordan 3 Black Cement was released,
في آخر مرةٍ تم إصدار Jordan 3 الاسمنت الأسود أُصدر،
at a retail of 160 dollars,
في بيع المفّرق بـ160 دولارًا،
it sold out globally in minutes.
تم بيعه عالميًا في دقائق.
And that's because people were camped outside of sneaker stores
و هذا لأن الناس كانوا يخيمون خارج متاجر الأحذية الرياضية
for days before it went on sale.
لأيام قبل عرضه للبيع.
And just minutes after that,
و بعد دقائق من ذلك،
thousands of those pairs were on eBay for two and three times retail.
الآلاف من تلك الأزواج تم بيعها على eBay لمرتين و ثلاثة في المفرّق.
In fact, there's over 1,000 pairs on eBay right now, four years later.
في الحقيقة، هناك أكثر من 1000 زوج على eBay الآن، بعد 4 سنوات.
But here's the thing:
لكن إليك هذا:
this happens every single Saturday.
هذا يحدث كل يوم سبت.
Every week there's another release or two or three,
كل أسبوع هناك إصدارٌ أخر أو حتى اصدارين أو ثلاثة،
and every shoe has a story
و كل حذاء لديه قصةٌ
as rich and compelling as the Jordan 3 Black Cement.
غنيةٌ و مقنعةٌ كما Joradn 3 الإسمنت الأسود.
This is Nike building the marketplace for sneakerheads --
هذا هو بناء Nike السوق التجاري لمدمني الأحذية الرياضية --
people who collect sneakers --
الأشخاص الذين يجمعون الأحذية الرياضية --
and my daughter.
و ابنتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's an "I love Dad" T-shirt.
هذا قميص "أحبك أبي"
For the brands, sneakerheads are a very important demographic.
يشكل محبي الأحذية الرياضية ديموغرافية مهمة جدا للعلامات التجارية.
These are the tastemakers; these are the Apple fanboys.
هؤلاء هم صانعي الأذواق؛ هؤلاء هم المعجبون ب Apple.
Because who else is going to buy
لأنه من غيرهم سيشتري
a pair of $8,000 Back to the Future sneakers?
زوجًا من الأحذية الرياضية لفلم العودة إلى المستقبل ب8،000$؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, 8,000 dollars.
نعم، 8،000 دولارًا.
And while that's obviously the anomaly,
و بينما من الواضح أن هذا غير طبيعي،
the resell sneaker market is definitely not.
فإن إعادة بيع الأحذية الرياضية ليست كذلك بالتأكيد.
Thirty years in the making,
ثلاثون سنة في التصنيع،
what started as an underground culture
ما بدأ كثقافةٍ سرية
of a few people who like sneakers just a bit too much --
لعددٍ من الأشخاص الذين يحبون الأحذية الرياضية أكثر قليلًا --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now we have sneaker addictions.
الآن لدينا إدمانٌ على أحذية رياضية.
In a market where in the past 12 months,
في سوقٍ منذ 12 شهرًا،
there have been over nine million pairs of shoes
تم اعادة بيع أكثر من 9 ملايين زوجٍ من الأحذية الرياضية
resold in the United States alone,
في الولايات المتحدة فقط،
at a value of 1.2 billion dollars.
ما قيمته 1.2 مليار دولار.
And that's a conservative estimate --
و هذا تقديرٌ متحفط --
I should know, I am a sneakerhead.
علي معرفة هذا، أنا مدمن أحذية رياضية.
This is my collection.
هذه مجموعتي.
In the pantheon of great collections, mine doesn't even register.
و في مجمعٍ للمجموعات الكبيرة، مجموعتي لا يحق لها التسجيل.
I have about 250 pairs, but trust me, I am small-time.
لدي حوالي 250 زوجًا، لكن ثقوا بي، أنا لا شيء.
People have thousands.
هناك أشخاصٌ لديهم آلاف.
I'm a very typical 37-year-old sneakerhead.
أنا عادي جدًا مدمن أحذيةٍ رياضية بعمر 37.
I grew up playing basketball when Michael Jordan played,
نشأت و أنا ألعب كرة السلة عندما كان مايكل جوردان يلعب،
I always wanted Air Jordans,
رغبت دائما أحذية Air Jordans
my mother would never buy me Air Jordans,
أمي لم تشتري لي Air Jordans أبدًا،
as soon as I got some money I bought Air Jordans --
و حالما امتلكت بعض المال اشتريت Air Jordans --
literally, we all have the exact same story.
حرفيًا، جمعينا نملك ذات القصة بالضبط.
But here's where mine diverged.
لكن هنا قصتي انحرفت.
After starting three companies, I took a job as a strategy consultant,
بعد انشاء ثلاث شركات، عملت كمستشار استرتيجيات،
when I very quickly realized that I didn't know the first thing about data.
عندما أدركت بسرعة أنني لم أعرف شيئًا عن البيانات.
But I learned, because I had to,
لكنني تعلمت، لأنه كان علي ذلك،
and I liked it.
و أحببته.
So I thought, I wonder if I could get ahold of some sneaker data,
ففكرت، أتسائل إن أستطعت الحصول على شيءٍ من بعض بيانات الأحذية الرياضية,
just to play with for my own amusement.
للعب بها و تسلية نفسي.
The goal was to develop a price guide,
كان الهدف تطوير مرشدٍ للأسعار،
a real data-driven view of the market.
وجهة نظر تعتمد البيانات الحقيقية للسوق.
And four years later, we're analyzing over 25 million transactions,
و بعد 4 سنوات، نحن نحلل أكثر من 25 مليون عملية،
providing real-time analytics on thousands of sneakers.
معطين تحليلات مباشرة لآلافٍ من الأحذية الرياضية.
Now sneakerheads check prices while camping out for releases.
و الآن يراجع مدمنو الأحذية الرياضية حين يخيمون منتظرين الإصدارات.
Others have used the data to validate insurance claims.
آخرون استعملوا البيانات لتقييم مطالبات التأمين.
And the top investment banks in the world
و البنوك ذات الاستثمارات الكبرى في العالم
now use resell data to analyze the retail footwear industry.
تستعمل الآن بيانات اعادة البيع لتحليل بيع المفرق لصناعة الأحذية.
And here's the best part:
و هنا الجزء الأفضل:
sneakerheads have sneaker portfolios.
مدمنو الأحذية الرياضية لديهم حقائب وزارية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sneakerheads can track the value of their collection over time,
يستطيع مدمنو الأحذية الرياضية متابعة قيمة مجموعاتهم مع الوقت،
compare it to others,
مقارنتها مع آخرى،
and have access to the same analytics you might
ويستطيعون الولوج إلى ذات التحليلات المرادة
for your online brokerage account.
من سمسار الحساب الالكتروني.
So sneakerhead Dan builds his collection and identifies which 352 are his.
إذًا مدمن الأحذية الرياضية دان بنى مجموعته و عرّفها ب 352 زوج يملكها.
He can see it's worth 103,000 dollars --
يستطيع ان يرى أن قيمتها 103,000 دولار --
frankly, a modest collection.
بصراحة، إنها مجموعة متواضعة.
At the asset level, he can see gain-loss by shoe.
بمستوى الأصول، يستطيع أن يرى بيانات الربح/الخسارة لكل حذاء.
Here he's made over 600 dollars on one pair.
هنا ربح أكثر من 600 دولارًا بحذاءٍ واحد.
I have one of those.
لدي واحد منها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So an unregulated 1.2 billion dollar industry
إذًَا صناعة ال 1.2 مليار دولار الغير منظمة
that thrives as much on the street as it does online,
تزدهر في الشارع كما تفعل في الانترنت،
and has spawned fundamental financial services for sneakers?
و أنتجت خدماتٍ ماليةٍ أساسية لأحذية رياضية؟
At some point I asked myself what's really going on in the market,
في لحظة ما سألت نفسي ما الذي يحدث حقيقةً في السوق،
and two comparisons started to emerge.
و بدأت مقارنتان اثنتان بالظهور.
Are sneakers more like stocks or drugs?
هل الأحذية الرياضية كالأسهم أو المخدرات؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In fact, one guy emailed to say
في الحقيقية، راسلني أحد الأشخاص يقول
he thought his 15-year-old son was selling drugs
أنه اعتقد أن ابنه ذو ال 15 عامًا كان يبيع المخدرات
and later found out he was selling sneakers.
و اكتشف بعد ذلك أنه كان يبيع الأحذية الرياضية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And now they use the data to do it together.
و الآن يستعملون البيانات و يفعلون ذلك معًا.
And that's because sneakers are an investment opportunity
و هذا لأن الأحذية الرياضية فرصة استثمارية
where none other exists.
عند عدم وجود أخرى.
And I don't just mean the kid selling sneakers instead of drugs.
و أن لا أعني بقولي أن الطفل يبيع الأحذية الرياضية بدل المخدرات.
How about all kids?
ماذا عن جميع الأطفال؟
You have to be 18 to play the stock market.
علينا أن نكون في ال18 للخوض في سوق الأسهم.
I sold chewing gum in sixth grade,
بعتُ العلكة في الصف السادس،
Blow Pops in ninth grade
المصاصات في صف التاسع
and collected baseball cards through high school.
و جمعت بطاقات البايسبول في الثانوية.
The cards are long dead,
انقرضت البطاقات منذ زمن طويل،
and the candy market's usually quite local.
و سوق الحلوى في العادة يكون محلي.
For a lot of people, sneakers are a legal and accessible investment opportunity --
للعديد من الأشخاص، الأحذية الرياضية فرصة استثمارية سهلة و قانونية --
a democratized stock market,
سوق أسهم ديموقراطية،
but also unregulated.
و لكن غير منظمة أيضًا.
Which is why the story you're probably most familiar with
لهذا تكون القصة التي تسمعونها في العادة
is people killing each other for sneakers.
أن الناس يقتلون بعضهم من أجل حذاءٍ رياضي.
And while that definitely happens and is tragic,
و بينما الذي يحدث بالتأكيد مأساوي،
it's not nearly the epidemic some media would have you believe.
فإنه ليس قريبًا من المعمعة التي تثيرها الصحافة التي تصدقونها.
In fact, it's a very small piece of a much bigger and better story.
في الحقيقة، إنه قطعة صغيرة جدًا من قصة أفضل و أكبر.
So sneakers have clear similarities
فلدى أحذية الرياضة أوجه تشابه واضحة
to both the stock exchange and the illegal drug trade,
لكلا سوق الأسهم و تجارة المخدرات الغير قانونية،
but perhaps the most fundamental is the existence of a central actor.
لكن ربما الشيء الأساسي هو وجود فاعل مركزي.
Someone is making the rules.
شخصٌ يضع القواعد.
In the case of sneakers, that someone is Nike.
في حالة الأحذية الرياضية، الشخص هو Nike.
Let me walk you through some numbers.
دعوني أخوض بكم بعض الأرقام.
The resell market, we know, is $1.2 billion.
قيمة سوق إعادة البيع التي نعرفها، 1.2 مليار.
Nike, including Jordan brand,
Nike، بما فيها ماركة Jordan،
accounts for 96 percent of all shoes sold on the secondary market.
حساباتهم تبلغ 96% من كل الأحذية التي تباع في السوق الثانوي.
Just complete domination.
سيطرة كاملة البتة.
Sneakerheads love Jordans.
مدمنو الأحذية الرياضية يعشقون Jordan.
And profit on the secondary market is about a third.
و مكاسب السوق الثانوي حوالي الثلث.
That means that sneakerheads made 380 million dollars
هذا يعني مدمنو الأحذية الرياضية يجنون 380 مليون دولارًا
selling Nikes last year.
ببيع Nike السنة الماضية.
Let's jump to retail for a second.
دعونا ننتقل إلى المفرق لبرهة.
Skechers, earlier this year,
Skechers، في بداية هذه السنة،
became the number two footwear brand in the country,
أصبحت الماركة رقم 2 للأحذية في البلاد،
surpassing Adidas -- this was a big deal.
متخطيةً, Adidas -- هذا أمر خطير.
And in the 12 months ending in June,
و في 12 شهرًا ينتهون في يونيو،
Skechers's net income was 209 million dollars.
كان المربح الصافي ل Skechers 209 مليون دولارًا.
That means that Nike's customers
هذا يعني ان زبائن Nike
make almost twice as much profit as their closest competitor.
يجنون تقريبًا ضعف المرابح لمنافسهم الأقرب.
That --
هذا --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How is that even possible?
كيف من الممكن حدوث هذا؟
The sneaker market is just supply and demand,
سوق الأحذية الرياضية عبارة عن عرض و طلب،
but Nike's gotten very good at using supply -- limited sneakers --
لكن Nike أصبحت جيدة جدًا في العرض -- إصدارات أحذية رياضية محدودة --
and the distribution of those sneakers to their own benefit.
و توزيع تلك الأحذية الرياضية لمصلحتهم الخاصة.
So it's really just supply.
فهي عبارة عن عرضٍ فقط.
Sneakerheads joke that as long as it's limited and Nike, they'll buy it.
مدمنوا الأحذية الرياضية لديهم نكتة طالما أنه Nike و اصدار محدود، اشتريه.
Shoes that sell for 8,000 dollars do so because they're very rare.
الأحذية التي تباع ب 8000 دولار تباع لإنها نادرة جدًا.
It's no different than any other collectible market,
إنها ليست مختلفة عن مثيلتها في السوق،
only this isn't a market at all.
لكن هذا ليس سوقًا البتة.
It's a false construct created by Nike --
إنها تركيبة مزورة أنشأتها Nike --
ingeniously created by Nike, in the most positive sense -- to sell more shoes.
بشكلٍ مبدع من Nike، في المعنى الإيجابي لبيع أحذيةٍ أكثر.
And in the process,
و على المدى البعيد،
it provided tens of thousands of people with life-long passions,
أوردت العشرات من الآلاف من الأشخاص بعشقٍ لطول الحياة،
myself included.
أنا نفسي أيضًا.
If Nike wanted to kill the resell market, they could do so tomorrow,
لو أرادت Nike إنهاء سوق إعادة البيع لفعلوه غدًا،
all they have to do is release more shoes.
كل ما عليهم هو إطلاق المزيد من الأحذية.
But we certainly don't want them to, nor is it in their best interest.
و لكننا بالتأكيد لن نريدهم أن يفعلوا هذا، و ليست ايضًا من مصالحهم الكبرى.
That's because unlike Apple, who will sell an iPhone to anyone who wants one,
لأنه على عكس Apple، التي تبيع iPhone لكل من يريد واحدًا،
Nike doesn't make their money by just selling $200 sneakers.
Nike لا تصنع أموالها عن طريق بيع حذاءٍ رياضي ب 200$
They sell millions of shoes to millions of people for 60 dollars.
إنهم يبيعون ملايين الأحذية لملايين الأشخاص ب 60 دولارًا.
And sneakerheads are the ones who drive the marketing
و مدمنو الأحذية الرياضية هم من يقود التسويق.
and the hype and the PR and the brand cachet,
و الدعاية و العلاقات العامة و ختم العلامة التجارية،
and enable Nike to sell millions of $60 sneakers.
و يجعلون Nike تبيع ملايين الأحذية الرياضية ل 60$.
It's marketing.
إنه التسويق.
It's marketing the likes of which has never been seen before --
إنه التسويق الغير مسبوق و لم يرى من قبل --
this isn't in any textbook.
إنه ليس في أي كتاب.
For 15 years Nike has propped up an artificial commodities market,
لمدة 15 سنة، و Nike تدعم سوق السلع الاصطناعية،
with a Facebook-level hyped IPO every single weekend.
بطرحٍ أولي عام يفوق مستوى الفيسبوك كل أسبوع.
Drive by any Footlocker at 8am on a Saturday morning,
عرّج على أي محل للأحذية الساعة 8 صباحاً صباح السبت.
and there will be a line down the street and around the block,
و ستجد صفًا على طول الشارع و يدور حول الأبنية،
and sometimes those kids have been waiting there all week.
و أحيانًا يكون هؤلاء الأطفال ينتظرون طوال الأسبوع.
You know those crazy iPhone lines you see on the news every other year?
هلى تعرفون تلك صفوف الدور المجنونة للأيفون التي تشاهد في الأخبارعند كل سنة؟
Nike lines happen 104 times more often.
صفوف دور Nike تحدث 104 مرات أكثر.
So Nike sets the rules.
إذًا Nike تشرّع القوانين.
And they do so by controlling supply and distribution.
و يفعلون هذا عن طريق التحكم في العرض و التوزيع.
But once a pair leaves the retail channel, it's the Wild West.
و لكن لحظة مغادرة زوجٍ بيع المفرّق، يسود الغرب المتوحش.
There are very few -- if any -- legal, unregulated markets of this size.
هناك عدد قليل- إن كان موجوداً - من الأسواق القانونية غيرالمنظمة بهذا الحجم.
So Nike is definitely not the stock exchange.
إذاً ليست Nike في النهاية سوق تبادل الأسهم.
In fact, there is no central exchange.
في الحقيقة، ليس هناك سوق تبادل مركزي.
By last count, there were 48 different online markets that I know of.
عند آخر إحصاء، كان هناك 48 سوق على الإنترنت مختلف أعرفها.
Some are eBay clones, some are mobile markets,
بعضها شبيهة ب eBay، و أخرى أسواقٌ متنقلة،
and then you have consignment shops and brick-and-mortar stores,
و لديك محلات البيع بالعمولة و محلات brick-and-mortar،
and sneaker conventions, and reseller sites,
و اتفاقيات الأحذية الرياضية و مواقع بيع التجزئة
and Facebook and Instagram and Twitter --
و الفيسبوك و الانستغرام وتويتر --
literally, anywhere sneakerheads come into contact with each other,
حرفيًا، في أي مكان يتواصل مدمنوا الأحذية الرياضية مع بعضهم البعض،
shoes will be bought and sold.
تباع الأحذية و تُشترى.
But that means no efficiencies, no transparency,
و لكن هذا يعني عدم الكفاءة، عدم الشفافية،
sometimes not even authenticity.
و في بعض الأحيان عدم الموثوقية.
Can you imagine if that's how stocks were bought?
هل يمكنك أن تتخيل كيف يتم شراء الأسهم؟
What if the way to buy a share of Apple stock
ماذا لو كانت طريقة شراء أسهم Apple
was to search over 100 places online and off,
كانت عن طريق البحث في أكثر من 100 موقع،
including every time you walk down the street
متضمنةً جميع الأوقات التي كنت تمشي فيها بالشارع
just hoping to pass someone wearing some Apple stock?
متأملًا المرور بشخصٍ يلبس بعض أسهم Apple؟
Never knowing who had the best price,
مع عدم معرفة من لديه السعر الأمثل،
or even if the stock you were looking at was real.
أو حتى إن كان السوق الذي تنظر إليه حقيقيًا حتى.
That would surely make you say:
هذا ما سيدفعك للسؤال:
[WTF?]
[ما هذا الهراء؟]
Of course that's not how we buy stock.
بالطبع هذه ليست طريقة شراء الأسهم.
But what if that's not how we need to buy sneakers either?
و لكن ماذا لو لم تكن أيضًا هي الطريقة لشراء أحذيةٍ رياضية؟
What if the inverse is true,
ماذا لو كان العكس صحيح،
and what if we could buy sneakers
و ماذا لو كنا نستطيع شراء الأحذية الرياضية
exactly the same way as we buy stock?
تمامًا كما نشتري الأسهم؟
And what if it wasn't just sneakers, but any similar product,
و ماذا لو لم تكن مجرد أحذيةٍ رياضية، بل أي منتج مشابه،
like watches and handbags and women's shoes,
كالساعات و الحقائب و الأحذية النسائية،
and any collectible, any seasonal item and any markdown item?
و أي شيٍ للتجميع، أي منتج موسمي، أي منتجٍ منخفض السعر؟
What if there was a stock market for commerce?
ماذا لو كان هناك سوق أسهمٍ للتجارة؟
A stock market of things.
سوق أسهمٍ لأشياء.
And not only could you buy in a much more educated and efficient manner,
و ليس شراء أشياءٍ أكثر بطريقة حضارية و فعالة أكثر فقط،
but you could engage in all the sophisticated financial transactions
بل الإنخراط في جميع التعاملات المالية المتقدمة
you can with the stock market.
في سوق الأسهم.
Shorts and options and futures
السراويل و خيارات و عقود آجلة
and well, maybe you see where this is going.
و أيضًا، ربما تستطيعون رؤية إلى أين يمكن الوصول.
Maybe you want to invest in a stock market of things.
ربما أردتم الاستثمار في سوق أسهم الأشياء.
Because if you had invested in a pair of Air Jordan 3 Black Cement in 2011,
لأنك إت كنت قد استثمرت في زوجٍ من Air Jordan الاسمنت الأسود عام 2011،
you could either be wearing them onstage,
ممكن أن ترتديهم على المسرح،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
or have earned 162 percent on your money --
أو تكون قد جنيت 162% من أموالك --
double the S&amp;P and 20 percent more than Apple.
ضعف أسهم S&amp;P و 20% من Apple.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's why we're talking about sneakers.
و لهذا نتكلم عن الأحذية الرياضية.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)